<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="UTF-8" ?>
  <page>
    <title>Cat</title>
    <id>6678</id>
    <revision>
      <id>182424966</id>
      <timestamp>2008-01-06T00:55:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anastrophe.</username>
        <id>473822</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>please add date modifier to fact tags for categorization. fixed typo also</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve"><template head="pp-semi-protected"><field name="small">yes</field></template>
<template head="about"><field>domestic felines</field></template>
<summary><p>&lt;!--- per <link label="Wikipedia:Manual of Style (spelling)">Wikipedia:Manual of Style (spelling)</link>, articles should conform to one overall spelling style of English, typically the one most linked to the article topic (if it is geographic based in some way) or the one it was created in. This article was created with American English. --&gt;
<template head="Taxobox"><field name="color"> pink
</field><field name="name"> Cat&lt;ref name=msw3&gt;<template head="MSW3 Wozencraft"><field name="pages"> 534–535</field></template>&lt;/ref&gt;
</field><field name="status"> <template head="StatusDomesticated"></template>
</field><field name="image"> Bengal_Cat_(Fia).jpg&lt;!--please do not change this image without first discussing on the talk page and reaching consensus. Undiscussed changes will be reverted.--&gt;
</field><field name="image_caption"> <link label="Commons:Category:Felis silvestris catus">other images of cats</link> 
</field><field name="image_width"> 250px
</field><field name="regnum"> <link label="Animal">Animal</link>ia
</field><field name="phylum"> <link label="Chordate">Chordata</link>
</field><field name="classis"> <link label="Mammal">Mammal</link>ia
</field><field name="ordo"> <link label="Carnivora">Carnivora</link>
</field><field name="familia"> <link label="Felidae">Felidae</link>
</field><field name="genus"> <i><link label="Felis">Felis</link></i>
</field><field name="species"> <i><link label="Wildcat">F. silvestris</link></i>
</field><field name="subspecies"> <b><i>F. s. catus</i></b>
</field><field name="trinomial"> <i>Felis silvestris catus</i>
</field><field name="trinomial_authority"> (<link label="Carolus Linnaeus">Linnaeus</link>, 1758)
</field><field name="synonyms"> &lt;small&gt;<i>Felis lybica</i> invalid <link label="Junior synonym">junior synonym</link>&lt;br&gt;<i>Felis catus</i> invalid junior synonym<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title"> <i>Felis catus</i> </field><field name="url"> http://www.itis.gov/servlet/SingleRpt/SingleRpt?search_topic=TSN&amp;search_value=183798 </field><field name="accessdate"> 2007-07-06</field></template></ref>&lt;/small&gt;
</field></template>
<template head="Spoken Wikipedia-3"><field>2007-05-13</field><field>En-Cat_(part_1).ogg</field><field>En-Cat_(part_2).ogg</field><field>En-Cat_(part_3).ogg</field><field></field></template>
<template head="portalpar"><field>Cats</field></template></p>

<p>The <b>Cat</b> (<i>Felis silvestris catus</i>), also known as the <b>Domestic Cat</b> or <b>House Cat</b> to distinguish it from other <link label="Felidae">felines</link>, is a small <link label="Carnivore">carnivorous</link> <link label="Species">species</link> of <link label="Crepuscular">crepuscular</link> <link label="Mammal">mammal</link> that is often valued by <link label="Human">human</link>s for its companionship and its ability to hunt <link label="Vermin">vermin</link>. It has been associated with humans for at least 9,500 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;9500 years&quot;&gt;<template head="cite web"><field name="title"> Oldest Known Pet Cat? 9500-Year-Old Burial Found on Cyprus </field><field name="url"> http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2004/04/0408_040408_oldestpetcat.html </field><field name="accessdate"> 2007-03-06 </field><field name="date"> 2004-04-08 </field><field name="publisher"> National Geographic News</field></template>&lt;/ref&gt;  </p>

<p>A skilled <link label="Predator">predator</link>, the cat is known to hunt over 1,000 species for food. It is <link label="Cat intelligence">intelligent</link> and can be trained to obey simple commands. Individual cats have also been known to learn to manipulate simple mechanisms, such as doorknobs. Cats use a variety of vocalizations and types of <link label="Cat body language">body language</link> for <link label="Cat communication">communication</link>, including <link label="Meow">meow</link>ing, <link label="Purr">purr</link>ing, <link label="Hissing">hissing</link>, <link label="Growling">growling</link>, squeaking, <link label="Chirp">chirp</link>ing, <link label="Click consonant">clicking</link>, and grunting.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url"> http://www.channel3000.com/news/1472741/detail.html </field><field name="title"> Meows Mean More To Cat Lovers </field><field name="publisher"> Channel3000.com </field><field name="accessdate"> 2006-06-14</field></template></ref> Cats are popular pets and are also bred and shown as <link label="Cat registry">registered</link> pedigree pets. This hobby is known as the &quot;Cat Fancy&quot;.</p>

<p>A study by the <link label="National Cancer Institute">National Cancer Institute</link> published in the journal <i><link label="Science (journal)">Science</link></i> says that all house cats are descended from a group of self-domesticating <link label="Felis silvestris lybica">desert wildcat</link>s <i>Felis silvestris lybica</i> circa 10,000 years ago, in the <link label="Near East">Near East</link>. All wildcat subspecies can interbreed, but domestic cats are all genetically contained within <i>F. s. lybica</i>. <ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title"> The Near Eastern Origin of Cat Domestication </field><field name="url"> http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/abstract/1139518</field><field name="accessdate"> June 30 </field><field name="accessyear"> 2007</field></template></ref></p>
</summary><section depth="1"><title>Physiology</title><section depth="2"><title>Size</title>

<p><img src="Cat anatomy diagram.svg">right|350px|thumb|Diagram of the general anatomy of a male cat.</img>
Cats typically weigh between 2.5 and 7&amp;nbsp;kg (5.5–16&amp;nbsp;pounds); however, some <link label=":Category:Cat breeds">breeds</link>, such as the <link label="Maine Coon">Maine Coon</link>, can exceed 11.3&amp;nbsp;kg (25&amp;nbsp;pounds). Some have been known to reach up to 23&amp;nbsp;kg (50&amp;nbsp;pounds) due to overfeeding. Conversely, very small cats (less than 1.8&amp;nbsp;kg / 4.0&amp;nbsp;lb)<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url"> http://www.messybeast.com/dwarfcats.html </field><field name="title"> DWARF, MIDGET AND MINIATURE CATS </field><field name="accessdate"> 2007-03-06</field></template></ref> have been reported. </p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Skeleton</title>

<p>Cats have 7 <link label="Cervical vertebrae">cervical vertebrae</link> like almost all mammals, 13 <link label="Thoracic vertebrae">thoracic vertebrae</link> (humans have 12), 7 <link label="Lumbar vertebrae">lumbar vertebrae</link> (humans have 5), 3 <link label="Sacral vertebrae">sacral vertebrae</link> like most mammals (humans have 5 because of their bipedal posture), and, except for <link label="Manx cat">Manx cat</link>s, 22 or 23 <link label="Caudal vertebrae">caudal vertebrae</link> (humans have 3 to 5, fused into an internal <link label="Coccyx">coccyx</link>). The extra lumbar and thoracic vertebrae account for the cat's enhanced spinal mobility and flexibility, compared with humans. The caudal vertebrae form the tail, used by the cat as a counterbalance to the body during quick movements. Cats also have free-floating <link label="Clavicle">clavicle bones</link>, which allows them to pass their body through any space into which they can fit their head.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title"> Cat Skeleton </field><field name="url"> http://bioweb.uwlax.edu/zoolab/Table_of_Contents/Lab-9b/Cat_Skeleton_1/cat_skeleton_1.htm </field><field name="accessdate"> 2006-12-12</field></template></ref></p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Mouth</title>

<p>Cats have highly specialized <link label="Tooth">teeth</link> for the tearing of meat. The <link label="Premolar">premolar</link> and <link label="Molar (tooth)">first molar</link> together compose the <link label="Carnassial">carnassial</link> pair on each side of the mouth, which efficiently functions to shear meat like a pair of <link label="Scissors">scissors</link>. While this is present in <link label="Canidae">canids</link>, it is highly developed in felines. The cat's <link label="Tongue">tongue</link> has sharp spines, or <link label="Papillae">papillae</link>, useful for retaining and ripping flesh from a carcass. These papillae are small backward-facing hooks that contain <link label="Keratin">keratin</link> which also assist in their grooming. </p>

<p>As facilitated by their oral structure, cats use a variety of vocalizations and types of <link label="Cat body language">body language</link> for <link label="Cat communication">communication</link>, including mewing (&quot;meow&quot; or &quot;miaow&quot;), <link label="Purr">purr</link>ing, hissing, <link label="Growling">growling</link>, squeaking, <link label="Chirp">chirp</link>ing, <link label="Click consonant">clicking</link>, and grunting.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url"> http://www.channel3000.com/news/1472741/detail.html </field><field name="title"> Meows Mean More To Cat Lovers </field><field name="publisher"> Channel3000.com </field><field name="accessdate"> 2006-06-14</field></template></ref></p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Ears</title>

<p>Thirty-two individual muscles in each ear allow for a manner of directional hearing:<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title"> At Home: Care / Health: Understanding Cats </field><field name="url"> http://www.hgtv.com/hgtv/ah_pets_care_health/article/0,1801,HGTV_3152_1380540,00.html </field><field name="accessdate"> 2005-08-15</field></template></ref> a cat can move each ear independently of the other. Because of this mobility, a cat can move its body in one direction and point its ears in another direction. Most cats have straight ears pointing upward. Unlike <link label="Dog">dog</link>s, flap-eared breeds are extremely rare. (<link label="Scottish Fold">Scottish Fold</link>s are one such exceptional <link label="Genetic mutation">genetic mutation</link>.) When angry or frightened, a cat will lay back its ears, to accompany the growling or hissing sounds it makes. Cats also turn their ears back when they are playing, or to listen to a sound coming from behind them. The angle of a cat's ears is an important clue to their mood.</p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Legs</title>

<p>Cats, like dogs, are <link label="Digitigrade">digitigrade</link>s: they walk directly on their toes, the bones of their feet making up the lower part of the visible leg. Cats are capable of walking very precisely, because like all <link label="Felines">felines</link> they directly register; that is, they place each hind paw (almost) directly in the print of the corresponding forepaw, minimizing noise and visible tracks. This also provides sure footing for their hind paws when they navigate rough terrain.</p>

<p>Unlike dogs and most mammals, cats walk by moving both legs on one side and then both legs on the other side. Most mammals move legs on alternate sides in sequence. Cats share this unusual <link label="Gait analysis">gait</link> with <link label="Camel">camel</link>s, <link label="Giraffe">giraffe</link>s, some horses ('pacers'), and a select few other mammals. There is no known connection between these animals which might explain this. </p>

<p>Like all members of <link label="Family (biology)">family</link> <link label="Felidae">Felidae</link> except the <link label="Cheetah">cheetah</link>, cats have retractable <link label="Claw">claw</link>s. In their normal, relaxed position the claws are sheathed with the skin and fur around the <link label="Paw">toe pads</link>. This keeps the claws sharp by preventing wear from contact with the ground and allows the silent stalking of prey. The claws on the forefeet are typically sharper than those on the hind feet.<ref> <template head="cite journal"><field name="title">Outline of Cat Lessons</field><field name="journal">The School Journal</field><field name="date">1900-12-22</field><field name="first">Annetta F.</field><field name="last">Armes</field><field name="coauthors"></field><field name="volume">LXI</field><field name="issue"></field><field name="pages">659</field><field name="id"> </field><field name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id=-_gBAAAAYAAJ</field><field name="format"></field><field name="accessdate">2007-11-12 </field></template></ref>  Cats can extend their claws voluntarily on one or more paws at will. They may extend their claws in hunting or self-defense, climbing, &quot;<link label="Kneading (cats)">kneading</link>&quot;, or for extra traction on soft surfaces (bedspreads, thick rugs, etc.). It is also possible to make a cooperative cat extend its claws by carefully pressing both the top and bottom of the paw. The curved claws may become entangled in carpet or thick fabric, which may cause injury if the cat is unable to free itself.</p>

<p>Most cats have five claws on their front paws, and four or five on their rear paws. Because of an ancient <link label="Mutation">mutation</link>, however, domestic cats are prone to <link label="Polydactyl cat">polydactyly</link>, and may have six or seven toes. The fifth front claw (the <link label="Dewclaw">dewclaw</link>) is in a more <link label="Anatomical terms of location">proximal</link> position than those of the other claws. More proximally, there is a protrusion which appears to be a sixth &quot;finger&quot;. This special feature of the front paws, on the inside of the wrists, is the carpal pad, also found on the paws of <link label="Big cat">big cat</link>s and <link label="Dog">dog</link>s. It has no function in normal walking, but is thought to be an anti-skidding device used while jumping.</p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Skin</title>

<p>Cats possess rather loose <link label="Skin">skin</link>; this allows them to turn and confront a predator or another cat in a fight, even when it has a grip on them. This is also an advantage for <link label="Veterinary medicine">veterinary</link> purposes, as it simplifies <link label="Injection (medicine)">injections</link>.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title"> Vaccinate Your Cat at Home </field><field name="url"> http://www.drsfostersmith.com/pic/article.cfm?aid=87 </field><field name="accessdate"> 2006-10-18</field></template></ref> In fact, the life of cats with <link label="Kidney failure">kidney failure</link> can sometimes be extended for years by the regular injection of large volumes of fluid subcutaneously, which serves as an alternative to <link label="Dialysis">dialysis</link>.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title"> The Cat Comes Back </field><field name="url"> http://www.wgrz.com/news/columnist/RKellman/KellmansCorner_article.aspx?storyid=37606 </field><field name="accessdate"> 2006-10-18</field></template></ref><ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title"> How to Give Subcutaneous Fluids to a Cat </field><field name="url"> http://www.wikihow.com/Give-Subcutaneous-Fluids-to-a-Cat </field><field name="accessdate"> 2006-10-18</field></template></ref></p>

<p>The particularly loose skin at the back of the neck is known as the <i>scruff</i>, and is the area by which a mother cat grips her <link label="Kitten">kitten</link>s to carry them. As a result, cats tend to become quiet and passive when gripped there. This tendency often extends into adulthood, and can be useful when attempting to treat or move an uncooperative cat. However, since an adult cat is heavier than a kitten, a pet cat should never be carried by the scruff, but should instead have their weight supported at the rump and hind legs, and at the chest and front paws. Often (much like a small child) a cat will lie with its head and front paws over a person's shoulder, and its back legs and rump supported under the person's arm.</p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Senses</title>

<template head="main"><link label="Cat senses">Cat senses</link></template>
<p>Cat senses are attuned for hunting. Cats have highly advanced hearing, eyesight, taste, and touch receptors, making the cat extremely sensitive among mammals. Cats' <link label="Night vision">night vision</link> is superior to humans although their <link label="Visual perception">vision</link> in daylight is inferior. Humans and cats have a similar range of <link label="Hearing (sense)">hearing</link> on the low end of the scale, but cats can hear much higher-pitched sounds, up to 64 <link label="Hertz">kHz</link>, which is 1.6 <link label="Octave">octave</link>s above the range of a human, and even one octave above the range of a dog.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url"> http://www.lsu.edu/deafness/HearingRange.html </field><field name="author">Strain, G.M. </field><field name="title">How Well Do Dogs and Other Animals Hear? </field><field name="publisher">Louisiana State University </field><field name="accessdate">2007-05-15</field></template></ref> A domestic cat's <link label="Olfaction">sense of smell</link> is about fourteen times as strong as a human's.&lt;ref name=&quot;senseofsmell&quot;&gt;<template head="cite web"><field name="url"> http://cats.about.com/cs/felineanatomy/a/catsnose_scent.htm </field><field name="title"> The Nose Knows </field><field name="publisher"> About.com </field><field name="accessdate"> 2006-11-29</field></template>&lt;/ref&gt; To aid with navigation and sensation, cats have dozens of movable <link label="Vibrissae">vibrissae</link> (whiskers) over their body, especially their face. Due to a mutation in an early cat ancestor, one of two genes necessary to taste <link label="Sweetness">sweetness</link> may have been lost by the cat family.&lt;ref name=sugar&gt;<template head="cite journal"><field name="last"> Li </field><field name="first"> Xia </field><field name="coauthors"> Weihua Li, Hong Wang, Jie Cao, Kenji Maehashi, Liquan Huang, Alexander A. Bachmanov, Danielle R. Reed, Véronique Legrand-Defretin, Gary K. Beauchamp, Joseph G. Brand </field><field name="title"> Pseudogenization of a Sweet-Receptor Gene Accounts for Cats' Indifference toward Sugar </field><field name="journal"> PLOS Genetics </field><field name="volume"> 1 </field><field name="issue"> 1 </field><field name="publisher"> <link label="Public Library of Science">Public Library of Science</link> </field><field name="month"> July </field><field name="year"> 2005 </field><field name="doi"> 10.1371/journal.pgen.0010003 </field><field name="accessdate"> 2006-11-08</field></template>&lt;/ref&gt;</p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Metabolism</title>

<p><img src="Cat-sleeping tortoiseshell cat-20051019.jpg">frame|right|250px|A cat sleeping curled into a tight ball to conserve body heat.</img>
Cats conserve energy by sleeping more than most animals, especially as they grow older. The daily duration of sleep varies, usually 12–16 hours, with 13–14 being the average. Some cats can sleep as much as 20 hours in a 24-hour period. The term <i>cat nap</i> refers to the cat's ability to fall asleep (lightly) for a brief period and has entered the English lexicon – someone who nods off for a few minutes is said to be &quot;taking a cat nap&quot;.</p>

<p>Due to their <link label="Crepuscular">crepuscular</link> nature, cats are often known to enter a period of increased activity and playfulness during the evening and early morning, dubbed the &quot;evening crazies&quot;, &quot;night crazies&quot;, &quot;elevenses&quot; or &quot;mad half-hour&quot; by some.<ref>Animal Doctor (July 9 2002). &quot;Dear Dr. Fox&quot;. <i>The Washington Post</i>, p. C10.</ref><ref><template head="cite book"><field name="author"> Ring, Ken and Romhany, Paul </field><field name="date"> <link label="1999-08-01">1999-08-01</link> </field><field name="title"> Pawmistry: How to Read Your Cat's Paws </field><field name="publisher"> Ten Speed Press </field><field name="location"> Berkeley, California </field><field name="pages"> p. 10 </field><field name="id"> ISBN 1-58008-111-8</field></template></ref></p>

<p>The temperament of a cat can vary depending on the breed and socialization. Cats with &quot;oriental&quot; body types tend to be thinner and more active, while cats that have a &quot;cobby&quot; body type tend to be heavier and less active. </p>

<p>The normal <link label="Thermoregulation">body temperature</link> of a cat is between 38 and 39 °<link label="Celsius">C</link> (101 and 102.2 °<link label="Fahrenheit">F</link>).<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title"> Normal Values For Dog and Cat Temperature, Blood Tests, Urine and other information in ThePetCenter.com </field><field name="url"> http://www.thepetcenter.com/exa/nv.html </field><field name="accessdate"> 2005-08-01</field></template></ref> A cat is considered <link label="Febrile">febrile</link> (<link label="Hyperthermia">hyperthermic</link>) if it has a temperature of 39.5&amp;nbsp;°C (103&amp;nbsp;°F) or greater, or <link label="Hypothermic">hypothermic</link> if less than 37.5&amp;nbsp;°C (100&amp;nbsp;°F). For comparison, humans have a normal temperature of approximately 36.8&amp;nbsp;°C (98.6&amp;nbsp;°F). A domestic cat's normal heart rate ranges from 140 to 220 beats per minute, and is largely dependent on how excited the cat is. For a cat at rest, the average heart rate should be between 150 and 180 bpm, about twice that of a human.</p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Genetics</title>

<p><img src="WhiteCat.jpg">left|thumb|250px|Blue-eyed cats with white fur have a reputation for having greater incidence of [[genetics|genetic</img> <link label="Deafness">deafness</link>.]]<template head="See also"><field>Cat coat genetics</field></template>&lt;!--original contents here were out-of-date genetics and incorrect. ---&gt;</p>

<p>A study by the <link label="National Cancer Institute">National Cancer Institute</link> published in the journal <i><link label="Science (journal)">Science</link></i> asserts that all house cats are descended from a group of self-domesticating <link label="Felis silvestris lybica">desert wildcat</link>s <i>Felis silvestris lybica</i> circa 10,000 years ago, in the <link label="Near East">Near East</link>. All wildcat subspecies can interbreed, but domestic cats are all genetically contained within <i>F. s. lybica</i>.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title"> The Near Eastern Origin of Cat Domestication </field><field name="url"> http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/abstract/1139518</field><field name="accessmonthday"> June 30 </field><field name="accessyear"> 2007</field></template></ref></p>

<p>The domesticated cat and its closest wild ancestor both possess 38 <link label="Chromosome">chromosome</link>s, in which over 200 heritable genetic defects have been identified, many homologous to human inborn errors. Specific metabolic defects have been identified underlying many of these feline diseases. There are several <link label="Gene">gene</link>s responsible for the hair color identified. The combination of them gives different <link label="Phenotype">phenotype</link>s.</p>

<p>Features like hair length, lack of tail or presence of a very short tail (bobtail cat) are also determined by single alleles and modified by polygenes.</p>

<p>The <b>Cat Genome Project</b>, sponsored by the Laboratory of Genomic Diversity at the U.S. <link label="National Cancer Institute">National Cancer Institute</link> Frederick Cancer Research and Development Center in <link label="Frederick, Maryland">Frederick, Maryland</link>, focuses on the development of the cat as an animal model for human hereditary disease, infectious disease, genome evolution, comparative research initiatives within the family Felidae, and forensic potential.</p>

<p>It is a common misconception that all white cats with blue eyes are <link label="Deaf">deaf</link>, leading to some people rejecting blue-eyed white cats as pets. This is not true, as there are many blue-eyed cats with perfect hearing. However, white cats with blue eyes do have slightly higher incidences of <link label="Genetics">genetic</link> <link label="Deafness">deafness</link> than white cats of other eye colors.</p>

<p>All felines, including the big cats, have a genetic anomaly that may prevent them from tasting sweetness,&lt;ref name=sugar/&gt; which is a likely factor for their usual indifference to or avoidance of fruits, berries, and other sugary foods.</p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Feeding and diet</title>

<p>Cats are classified as <link label="Obligate carnivores">obligate carnivores</link>, predominantly because their physiology is geared toward efficient processing of meat, and lacks efficient processes for digesting plant matter. Similarly as with its teeth, a cat's <link label="Gastrointestinal tract">digestive tract</link> has become specialized over time to suit meat eating, having shortened in length only to those segments of intestine best able to break down proteins and fats from animal flesh.<ref><template head="cite journal"><field name="author">Zoran DL </field><field name="title">The carnivore connection to nutrition in Cats </field><field name="journal">Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association </field><field name="volume">221 </field><field name="issue">11 </field><field name="pages">1559-67 </field><field name="year">2002 </field><field name="doi">10.2460/javma.2002.221.1559 </field><field name="url">http://www.catinfo.org/zorans_article.pdf</field></template></ref>  The trait severely limits the cat's ability properly to digest, metabolize, and absorb plant-derived nutrients, as well as certain <link label="Fatty acids">fatty acids</link>. For example, <link label="Taurine">taurine</link> is scarce in plants but abundant in meats. It is a key amino sulfonic acid for eye health in cats. Taurine deficiency can cause a condition called <link label="Macular degeneration">macular degeneration</link> wherein the cat's retina slowly degenerates, eventually causing irreversible blindness.  </p>

<p>Despite the cat's meat-oriented physiology, it is still quite common for a cat to supplement its carnivorous diet with small amounts of grass, leaves, shrubs, houseplants, or other plant matter anyway. One theory suggests this behavior helps cats regurgitate if their digestion is upset; another is that it introduces fiber or trace minerals into the diet. In this context, caution is recommended for cat owners because some houseplants are harmful to cats. For example, the leaves of the <link label="Lilium longiflorum">Easter Lily</link> can cause permanent and life-threatening kidney damage to cats, and <link label="Philodendron">Philodendron</link> are also poisonous to cats. The <link label="Cat Fanciers' Association">Cat Fanciers' Association</link> has a full list of plants harmful to cats.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url"> http://www.cfainc.org/articles/plants.html </field><field name="title"> Plants and Your Cat </field><field name="publisher"> The Cat Fanciers' Association, Inc. </field><field name="accessdate"> 2007-05-15</field></template></ref></p>

<p>An unsupplemented vegetarian diet cannot meet a cat's dietary requirements. Nevertheless, there are several vegetarian or vegan commercially-available cat foods supplemented with <link label="Chemical synthesis">chemically-synthesized</link> taurine and other added nutrients that attempt to address nutritional shortfalls. </p>

<p>Additionally, cats have been known to develop a fondness for prepared human foods, normally such entrees which are rich in proteins or fats. However, a diet consisting only of human food (even if high quality meat) is unlikely to contain the balanced nutrition required by the cat. Cats normally are good self-regulators of diet; however, unlimited access to food, or excessive human-food 'treats', will often lead to the cat becoming obese, particularly if it is older or more sedentary. This may lead to several health complications, such as diabetes, especially in neutered males. Such health conditions can be prevented through diet and exercise (playing), especially for cats living exclusively indoors. </p>

<p>Cats can be selective eaters (which may be due in some way to the aforementioned mutation which caused their species to lose sugar-tasting ability). Unlike most mammals, cats can voluntarily starve themselves indefinitely despite being presented with palatable food, even a food which they had previously readily consumed. This can happen when the <link label="Vomeronasal organ">vomeronasal or Jacobson's organ</link> becomes accustomed to a specific food, or if the cats are spoiled by their owners, in which case the cat will reject any food that does not fit the pattern it is expecting. It is also known for cats to merely become bored with their given food and decide to stop eating until they are tempted into eating again. Although it is extremely rare for a cat to deliberately starve itself to the point of injury, the sudden loss of weight can cause a fatal condition called <link label="Hepatic lipidosis">hepatic lipidosis</link>, a liver dysfunction which causes pathological loss of appetite and reinforces the starvation, which can lead to death within as little as 48 hours.</p>

<p>Some cats have a fondness for <link label="Catnip">catnip</link>, which is sensed by their <link label="Olfactory system">olfactory system</link>s. While they generally do not consume it, they will often roll in it, paw at it, and occasionally chew on it. The effect is usually relatively short, lasting for only a few minutes. After two hours or less, susceptible cats gain interest again. Several other species of plants (such as mint) cause this effect, to a lesser degree.</p>

<p>Cats can also develop <link label="Pica (disorder)">pica</link>. Pica is a condition in which animals chew or eat unusual things such as fabric, plastic or wool. In cats, this is mostly harmless as they do not digest most of it, but can be fatal or require surgical removal if a large amount of foreign material is ingested (for example, an entire sock). It tends to occur more often in Burmese, Oriental, Siamese and breeds with these in their ancestry.</p>
<section depth="3"><title>Toxic sensitivity</title>

<p>The liver of a cat is less effective at <link label="Detoxification">detoxification</link> than those of other animals, including humans and dogs; therefore exposure to many common substances considered safe for households may be dangerous to them.&lt;ref name=&quot;judy&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;vetinfo&quot;/&gt; In general, the cat's environment should be examined for the presence of such toxins and the problem corrected or alleviated as much as possible; in addition, where sudden or prolonged serious illness without obvious cause is observed, the possibility of toxicity must be considered, and the veterinarian informed of any such substances to which the cat may have had access.</p>

<p>For instance, the common painkiller <link label="Paracetamol">paracetamol</link> or <link label="Acetaminophen">acetaminophen</link>, sold under brand names such as <link label="Tylenol">Tylenol</link> and <link label="Panadol">Panadol</link>, is extremely toxic to cats; because they naturally lack enzymes needed to digest it, even minute portions of doses safe for humans can be fatal&lt;ref name=&quot;CanVetJ2003-Allen&quot;&gt;<template head="cite journal"><field name="author"> Allen AL </field><field name="title"> The diagnosis of acetaminophen toxicosis in a cat </field><field name="journal"> Canadian Veterinary Journal </field><field name="year"> 2003 </field><field name="pages"> 509-10 </field><field name="volume"> 44 </field><field name="issue"> 6 </field><field name="id"> PMID 12839249 </field><field name="url"> http://www.pubmedcentral.gov/articlerender.fcgi?tool=pubmed&amp;pubmedid=12839249</field></template>&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;vetinfo&quot;/&gt; and any suspected ingestion warrants immediate veterinary attention.&lt;ref name=&quot;VetHumToxicol1998-Villar&quot;&gt;<template head="cite journal"><field name="author"> Villar D, Buck WB, Gonzalez JM </field><field name="title"> Ibuprofen, aspirin and acetaminophen toxicosis and treatment in Dogs and Cats </field><field name="journal"> Vet Hum Toxicol </field><field name="year"> 1998 </field><field name="pages"> 156-62 </field><field name="volume"> 40 </field><field name="issue"> 3 </field><field name="id"> PMID 9610496</field></template>&lt;/ref&gt; Even <link label="Aspirin">aspirin</link>, which is sometimes used to treat <link label="Arthritis">arthritis</link> in cats, is much more toxic to them than to humans and must be administered cautiously.&lt;ref name=&quot;vetinfo&quot;/&gt; Similarly, application of <link label="Minoxidil">minoxidil</link> (<link label="Rogaine (drug)">Rogaine</link>) to the skin of cats, either accidental or by well-meaning owners attempting to counter loss of fur, has sometimes proved fatal.<ref><template head="cite journal"><field name="author"> Camille DeClementi </field><field name="coauthors"> Keith L. Bailey, Spencer C. Goldstein, and Michael Scott Orser </field><field name="title"> Suspected toxicosis after topical administration of minoxidil in 2 cats </field><field name="journal"> Journal of Veterinary Emergency and Critical Care </field><field name="year"> 2004 </field><field name="month"> December </field><field name="pages"> 287–292 </field><field name="volume"> 14 </field><field name="issue"> 4 </field><field name="id"> <template head="doi"><field>10.1111/j.1476-4431.2004.04014.x</field></template> </field><field name="accessdate"> 2007-01-18</field></template></ref><ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url"> http://www.showcatsonline.com/x/minoxidil.htm </field><field name="title"> Minoxidil Warning </field><field name="accessdate"> 2007-01-18 </field><field name="publisher"> ShowCatsOnline.com </field><field name="quote"> Very small amounts of Minoxidil can result [in] serious problems or death</field></template></ref></p>

<p>In addition to such obvious dangers as <link label="Insecticide">insecticide</link>s and <link label="Weed killer">weed killer</link>s, other common household substances that should be used with caution in areas where cats may be exposed to them include <link label="Mothball">mothball</link>s and other <link label="Naphthalene">naphthalene</link> products,&lt;ref name=&quot;vetinfo&quot;/&gt; as well as <link label="Phenol">phenol</link> based products often used for cleaning and disinfecting near cats' feeding areas or litter boxes, such as <link label="Pine-Sol">Pine-Sol</link>, <link label="Dettol">Dettol</link> (Lysol), <link label="Hexachlorophene">hexachlorophene</link>, <i>etc.</i>&lt;ref name=&quot;vetinfo&quot;&gt;<template head="cite web"><field name="url"> http://www.vetinfo4cats.com/ctoxin.html </field><field name="title"> Toxic to Cats </field><field name="accessdate"> 2007-01-18 </field><field name="publisher"> Vetinfo4Cats</field></template>&lt;/ref&gt; which, although they are widely used without problem, have been sometimes seen to be fatal.<ref><template head="cite journal"><field name="author"> Rousseaux CG, Smith RA, Nicholson S </field><field name="title"> Acute Pinesol toxicity in a domestic cat </field><field name="journal"> Vet Hum Toxicol </field><field name="year"> 1986 </field><field name="pages"> 316-7 </field><field name="volume"> 28 </field><field name="issue"> 4 </field><field name="id"> PMID 3750813 </field><field name="url"> http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=3750813&amp;dopt=Abstract</field></template></ref> <link label="Ethylene glycol">Ethylene glycol</link>, often used as an automotive <link label="Antifreeze">antifreeze</link>, is particularly appealing to cats, and as little as a teaspoonful can be fatal.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url"> http://www.cfainc.org/articles/antifreeze.html </field><field name="title"> Antifreeze Warning </field><field name="publisher"> The Cat Fanciers' Association, Inc. </field><field name="accessdate"> 2007-05-15</field></template></ref></p>

<p>Many human foods are somewhat toxic to cats; <link label="Theobromine">theobromine</link> in <link label="Chocolate">chocolate</link> can cause <link label="Theobromine poisoning">theobromine poisoning</link>, for instance, although few cats will eat chocolate. Toxicity in cats ingesting relatively large amounts of <link label="Onion">onion</link>s or <link label="Garlic">garlic</link> has also been reported.&lt;ref name=&quot;vetinfo&quot;/&gt; Even such seemingly safe items as <link label="Cat food">cat food</link> packaged in pull tab <link label="Tin can">tin can</link>s have been statistically linked to <link label="Hyperthyroidism">hyperthyroidism</link>; although the connection is far from proved, suspicion has fallen on the use of <link label="Bisphenol A">bisphenol A</link>, another phenol based product as discussed above, to seal such cans.&lt;ref name=&quot;vetinfo&quot;/&gt;</p>

<p>Many <link label="Houseplant">houseplant</link>s are at least somewhat toxic to many species, cats included&lt;ref name=&quot;judy&quot;&gt;<template head="cite web"><field name="url"> http://www.judyshealthcafe.com/articles/substances.html </field><field name="title"> Substances That Are Poison to Pets </field><field name="accessdate"> 2007-01-18 </field><field name="publisher"> Judy's Health Cafe.com</field></template>&lt;/ref&gt; and the consumption of such plants by cats is to be avoided.</p>
</section></section></section><section depth="1"><title>Behavior</title>
<template head="Refimprovesect"><field name="date">November 2007</field></template>
<template head="seealso"><field>Cat behavior</field><field>cat communication</field></template>
<section depth="2"><title>Sociability</title>
<p>For cats, life in close proximity with humans (and other animals kept by humans as pets) amounts to a &quot;symbiotic social adaptation&quot; which has developed over thousands of years. The sort of social relationship cats have with their human keepers is hard to map onto more generalized wild cat (Felis spp.) behavior, but it is certain that the cat thinks of humans differently than it does of cats (i.e., it does not think of itself as human, nor that humans are cats). This can be seen in the difference in body and vocal language it uses with humans, when compared to how it communicates with other cats in the household, for example. Some have suggested that, psychologically, the human keeper of a cat is a sort of surrogate for the cat's mother, and that adult domestic cats live their lives in a kind of extended kittenhood.<ref><external href="http://animal.discovery.com/guides/cats/body/maturity.html">Cat Guide: Adolescence and Sexual Maturity</external> Animal Planet</ref>
<img src="Tux and edo laying together.JPG‎">right|350px|thumb|Cats can befriend other cats. Here, two cats sleep together.</img></p>

<p>Cats may express affection towards their human companions, especially if they <link label="Imprinting (psychology)">imprint</link> on them at a very young age and are treated with consistent affection. Some breeds like the <link label="Bengal (cat)">Bengal</link>, <link label="Ragdoll">Ragdoll</link>, <link label="Pixie-Bob">Pixie-Bob</link>, <link label="Ocicat">Ocicat</link> and <link label="Manx (cat)">Manx</link> are known to be very social by instinct.<template head="Fact"><field name="date">January 2008</field></template></p>

<p>Regardless of the average sociability of any given cat or of cats in general, there are still any number of cats who meet or exceed the negative feline stereotype insofar as being poorly socialized. Yet with proper training and reinforcement of positive social behavior, poorly socialized cats can become more social over time.<template head="Fact"><field name="date">May 2007</field></template> Older cats have also been reported to sometimes develop aggressiveness towards kittens, which may include biting and scratching; this type of behavior is known as Feline Asocial Aggression.<ref><template head="cite journal"><field name="url"> http://faculty.washington.edu/jcha/330_cats_introducing.pdf </field><field name="format"> pdf </field><field name="title"> Intercat aggression in households following the introduction of a new cat </field><field name="author"> E. Levine </field><field name="coauthors"> P. Perry, J. Scarlett, K.A. Houpt </field><field name="journal"> Applied Animal Behaviour Science </field><field name="issue"> 90 </field><field name="year"> 2005 </field><field name="pages"> 325–336</field></template></ref></p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Cohabitation</title>

<p><img src="Greyandwhitecat.jpg">left|200px|thumb|An indoor/ outdoor grey and white cat prowling around.</img></p>

<p>One way that it is possible to see how house cats are naturally meant to behave is to observe feral domestic cats, which are social enough to form <link label="Feral cat colony">colonies</link>. Each cat in a colony holds a distinct territory, with sexually active males having the largest territories, and neutered cats having the smallest. Between these territories are neutral areas where cats watch and greet one another without territorial conflicts. Outside these neutral areas, territory holders usually aggressively chase away stranger cats, at first by staring, hissing, and growling, and if that does not work, by short but noisy and violent attacks.  </p>

<p>Despite cohabitation in colonies, cats do not have a social survival strategy, or a <link label="Pack mentality">pack mentality</link>. This mainly means that an individual cat takes care of all basic needs on its own (e.g., finding food, and defending itself), and thus cats are always lone hunters; they do not hunt in groups as <link label="Dog">dog</link>s or <link label="Lion">lion</link>s do.  (Of further note in this context is that it is no coincidence how cats frequently tonguebathe themselves (see Hygiene): the chemistry of their saliva, expended during their frequent grooming, appears to be a natural deodorant. Thus, a cat's cleanliness would aid in decreasing the chance a prey animal could notice the cat's presence. By contrast, dog odor is an advantage in hunting, for a dog is a pack hunter; part of the pack stations itself upwind, and its odor drives prey towards the rest of the pack stationed downwind. This requires a cooperative effort, which in turn requires communications skills. No such communications skills are required of a lone hunter.)</p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Fighting</title>
<p><img src="GAto.jpg">thumb|right|250px|Cats' acts of self defence involve arching their backs, turning sideways, and hissing</img>
When engaged in feline-to-feline combat for self-defense, territory, reproduction, or dominance, <link label="Catfight (animal behavior)">fighting cats</link> make themselves appear more impressive and threatening by raising their fur and arching their backs, thus increasing their apparent size. Cats also behave this way while playing. Attacks usually comprise powerful slaps to the face and body with the forepaws as well as bites, but serious damage is rare; usually the loser runs away with little more than a few scratches to the face, and perhaps the ears. Cats will also throw themselves to the ground in a defensive posture to rake with their powerful hind legs. Normally, serious negative effects will be limited to possible infections of the scratches and bites; though these have been known to sometimes kill cats if untreated. In addition, such fighting is believed to be the primary route of transmission of <link label="Feline immunodeficiency virus">feline immunodeficiency virus</link> (FIV). Sexually active males will usually be in many fights during their lives, and often have decidedly battered faces with obvious scars and cuts to the ears and nose. Not only males will fight; females will also fight over territory or to defend their kittens, and even neutered cats will defend their (smaller) territories aggressively.</p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Play</title>
<p>Domestic cats, especially young kittens, are known for their love of play. This behaviour mimics hunting and is important in helping kittens learn to stalk, capture and kill prey.<ref><template head="cite journal"><field name="author">Poirier FE, Hussey LK </field><field name="title">Nonhuman Primate Learning: The Importance of Learning from an Evolutionary Perspective </field><field name="journal">Anthropology &amp; Education Quarterly </field><field name="volume">13 </field><field name="issue">2 </field><field name="pages">133–148 </field><field name="year">1982 </field><field name="url">http://www.jstor.org/view/01617761/sp050045/05x1830j/0</field></template></ref> Many cats cannot resist a dangling piece of string, or a piece of rope drawn randomly and enticingly across the floor. This well known love of string is often depicted in cartoons and photographs, which show kittens or cats playing with balls of yarn. It is probably related to hunting instincts, including the common practice of kittens hunting their mother's and each other's tails. If string is ingested, however, it can become caught in the cat’s stomach or intestines, causing illness, or in extreme cases, death. Due to possible complications caused by ingesting a string, string play is sometimes replaced with a <link label="Laser pointer">laser pointer</link>'s dot, which some cats will chase. While caution is called for, there are no documented cases of feline eye damage from a laser pointer, and the combination of precision needed and low energy involved make it a remote risk. A common compromise is to use the laser pointer to draw the cat to a prepositioned toy so the cat gets a reward at the end of the chase.</p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Hunting</title>
<p><img src="Cat-eating-prey.jpg">right|thumb|250px|Domestic cat presenting a bird to its owner.</img> Cats have <link label="Evolution">evolved</link> to be <link label="Carnivore">carnivore</link>s and are highly specialized for hunting. Their style of hunting uses short bursts of intense exercise punctuating long periods of rest.   Much like their <link label="Big cat">big cat</link> relatives, domestic and feral cats are very effective predators<ref>http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/fwt/back_issues/december98/cats.html</ref>. Domestic felines ambush, or pounce, and immobilize vertebrate <link label="Predation">prey</link> using tactics similar to those of <link label="Leopard">leopard</link>s and <link label="Tiger">tiger</link>s.   After attacking prey cats deliver a lethal neck bite with their long <link label="Canine tooth">canine teeth</link> that severs the prey's <link label="Spinal cord">spinal cord</link>, causes fatal bleeding by puncturing the <link label="Carotid artery">carotid artery</link> or the <link label="Jugular vein">jugular vein</link>, or <link label="Asphyxiates">asphyxiates</link> the prey by crushing its <link label="Trachea">trachea</link>.</p>

<p>One poorly-understood element of cat hunting behaviour is the presentation of killed prey to human owners.  <link label="Ethology">Ethologist</link> Paul Leyhausen proposed that cats adopt humans into their social group, and share excess kill with others in the group according to the local pecking order, in which humans place at or near the top.<ref><template head="cite book"><field name="last">Leyhausen </field><field name="first">Paul </field><field name="title">Cat Behavior: The Predatory and Social Behavior of Domestic and Wild Cats </field><field name="year">1978 </field><field name="isbn">978-0824070175</field></template></ref>  Another possibility is that presenting the kill might be a relic of a kitten's behavior of demonstrating for its mother's approval that it has developed the necessary skill for hunting.  Indoor cats will often retain their hunting instinct and deliver small household items to their owners, such as watches, pens, pencils, and other objects they can carry in their mouths.  After depositing the item, they will meow to gain the attention of their owners. <template head="Fact"><field name="date">November 2007</field></template></p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Reproduction</title>
<template head="refimprovesect"><field name="date">December 2007</field></template>

<p>Cats are seasonally <link label="Polyestrous">polyestrous</link>, &lt;!-- I created a redirect to the <link label="Estrus cycle">Estrus cycle</link> article - but that claims cats are diestrous. Copyediting for consistency needed between the two articles! --&gt;which means they may have many periods of heat over the course of a year. A heat period lasts about 4 to 7 days if the female is bred; if she is not, the heat period lasts longer.</p>

<p>Multiple males will be attracted to a female in heat. The males will fight over her, and the victor wins the right to mate. At first, the female will reject the male, but eventually the female will allow the male to mate. The female will give a loud yowl as the male pulls out of her. After mating, the female will give herself a thorough wash. If a male attempts to breed with her at this point, the female will attack him. Once the female is done grooming, the cycle will repeat.</p>

<p>The male cat's <link label="Penis">penis</link> has spines which point backwards. Upon withdrawal of the penis, the spines rake the walls of the female's <link label="Vagina">vagina</link>, which may cause <link label="Ovulation">ovulation</link>. Because this does not always occur, females are rarely impregnated by the first male with which they mate. Furthermore, cats are <link label="Superfecundation">superfecund</link>; that is, a female may mate with more than one male when she is in heat, meaning different <link label="Kitten">kitten</link>s in a litter may have different fathers.</p>

<p><img src="Youngkitten.JPG">thumb|250px|right|A kitten with [[eye</img>s open for the first time.]] The <link label="Gestation">gestation</link> period for cats is approximately 63–65 days. The size of a <link label="Litter (animal)">litter</link> averages three to five kittens, with the first litter usually smaller than subsequent litters. Kittens are weaned at between six and seven weeks, and cats normally reach sexual maturity at 4–10 months (females) and to 5–7 months (males). </p>

<p>Cats are ready to go to new homes at about 12 weeks old (the recommended minimum age by Fédération Internationale Féline), or when they are ready to leave their mother. Cats can be surgically <link label="Sterilization (surgical procedure)">sterilized</link> (spayed or <link label="Castrated">castrated</link>) as early as 6–8 weeks to limit unwanted reproduction. This surgery also prevents undesirable sex-related behavior, such as <link label="Territorial marking">territory marking</link> (spraying urine) in males and yowling (calling) in females. If a cat is neutered after such behavior has been learned, however, then the behavior may persist.</p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Hygiene</title>

<p>Cats are known for their fastidious cleanliness. They <link label="Personal grooming">groom</link> themselves by licking their <link label="Fur">fur</link>, employing their hooked papillae and saliva. As mentioned, their <link label="Saliva">saliva</link> is a powerful cleaning agent and deodorant. Many cats also enjoy grooming humans or other cats. Sometimes the act of grooming another cat is initiated as an assertion of superior position in the pecking order of a group (dominance grooming).</p>

<p>Some cats occasionally regurgitate <link label="Hair balls">hair balls</link> of fur that have collected in their stomachs as a result of their grooming. Longhaired cats are more prone to this than shorthaired cats. Hairballs can be prevented with certain cat foods and remedies that ease elimination of the hair and regular grooming of the coat with a comb or stiff brush. Cats expend nearly as much fluid grooming as they do urinating.<template head="Fact"><field name="date">November 2007</field></template></p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Scratching</title>

<p>Cats are naturally driven to periodically hook their front claws into suitable surfaces and pull backwards, in order to clean the claws and remove the worn outer sheath as well as exercise and stretch their muscles. This scratching behavior seems enjoyable to the cat, and even <link label="#Declawing">declawed</link> cats will go through elaborate scratching routines with every evidence of great satisfaction, despite the total lack of results. </p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Fondness for heights</title>

<p><img src="Cat in tree03.jpg">thumb|250px|A cat in a tree.</img>
Most breeds of cat have a noted fondness for settling in high places, or perching. Animal behaviorists have posited a number of explanations, the most common being that height gives the cat a better observation point, allowing it to survey its &quot;territory&quot; and become aware of activities of people and other pets in the area. In the wild, a higher place may serve as a concealed site from which to hunt; domestic cats are known to strike prey by pouncing from such a perch as a tree branch, as does a <link label="Leopard">leopard</link>.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title">Why Do Cats Like High Places? </field><field name="publisher"> Dr. Holly Nash, DVM, MS </field><field name="url"> http://www.peteducation.com/article.cfm?cls=1&amp;cat=1313&amp;articleid=1125 </field><field name="work"> Drs. Foster &amp; Smith, Inc.</field></template></ref> Height, therefore, can also give cats a sense of security and prestige.</p>

<p>During a fall from a high place, a cat can reflexively twist its body and right itself using its acute <link label="Equilibrioception">sense of balance</link> and flexibility.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title"> Falling Cats </field><field name="url"> http://www.verrueckte-experimente.de/leseproben_e.html </field><field name="accessdate"> 2005-10-24</field></template></ref> This is known as the cat's &quot;<link label="Cat righting reflex">righting reflex</link>&quot;. It always rights itself in the same way, provided it has the time to do so, during a fall. The height required for this to occur in most cats (safely) is around 3&amp;nbsp;feet (90&amp;nbsp;cm).  Cats without a <link label="Tail (anatomy)">tail</link> also have this ability, since a cat mostly moves its hind legs and relies on conservation of <link label="Angular momentum">angular momentum</link> to set up for landing, and the tail is in fact little used for this feat.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url"> http://helix.gatech.edu/Classes/ME3760/1998Q3/Projects/Nguyen/ </field><field name="title">How does a Cat always land on its feet? </field><field name="author"> Huy D. Nguyen </field><field name="publisher"> Georgia Tech University, School of Medical Engineering </field><field name="accessdate"> 2007-05-15</field></template></ref></p>

<p>However, cats' fondness for high spaces can dangerously test the righting reflex. The <link label="American Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals">American Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals</link> warns owners to safeguard the more dangerous perches in their homes, to avoid &quot;<link label="High-rise syndrome">high-rise syndrome</link>&quot;, where an overconfident cat falls from an extreme height.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url">http://www.peteducation.com/article.cfm?cls=0&amp;cat=2032&amp;articleid=3409 </field><field name="title"> High-Rise Syndrome: Cats Injured Due to Falls </field><field name="author"> Veterinary &amp; Aquatic Services Department </field><field name="work"> Drs. Foster &amp; Smith, Inc.</field></template></ref></p>
</section></section><section depth="1"><title>Ecology</title><section depth="2"><title>Habitat</title>

<p>The <link label="African Wildcat">African Wildcat</link> (<i>Felis sylvestris lybica</i>), ancestor of the domestic cat, is believed to have evolved in a desert climate, as evident in the behavior common to both the domestic and wild forms. Wildcats (<i>Felis sylvestris</i>) are native to all continents other than Australia and Antarctica, although feral cats have become <link label="Apex predator">apex predator</link>s in the Australian Outback where they are menaces to wildlife.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url">http://www.abc.net.au/rn/science/ockham/stories/s64308.htm</field><field name="title">www.abc.net.au/rn/science/ockham/stories/s64308.htm&lt;!--INSERT TITLE--&gt;</field><field name="accessdate">2007-05-26</field></template></ref> Their feces are usually dry, and cats prefer to bury them in sandy places. Urine is highly concentrated, which allows the cat to retain as much fluid as possible. They are able to remain motionless for long periods, especially when observing prey and preparing to pounce. In North Africa there are still small wildcats that are probably related closely to the ancestors of today's domesticated cat breeds.</p>

<p><img src="Cat-sleeping-on-head.jpg">left|thumb|250px|Domestic cat enjoying heat near a window on a sunny day.</img>  Being closely related to desert animals, cats enjoy heat and solar exposure, often sleeping in a sunny area during the heat of the day, as part of a general preference for warm temperatures. Where humans typically start to feel uncomfortable when their skin temperature gets higher than about 44.5&amp;nbsp;°C (112&amp;nbsp;°F), by contrast cats do not start to show signs of discomfort until their skin reaches about 52&amp;nbsp;°C (126&amp;nbsp;°F).  </p>

<p>Overall, cats can easily withstand the heat and cold of a <link label="Temperate">temperate</link> climate, so long as the cold is not for extended periods. Although certain breeds such as the <link label="Norwegian Forest Cat">Norwegian Forest Cat</link> and <link label="Maine Coon">Maine Coon</link> have developed heavier coats of fur than other cats, they have little resistance against moist cold (e.g., fog, rain and snow) and struggle to maintain their 39&amp;nbsp;°C (102&amp;nbsp;°F) body temperature when wet. In direct relation to that fact, most cats dislike immersion in water. One major exception is the <link label="Turkish Van">Turkish Van</link> breed which has an unusual fondness for water.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url">http://www.swimmingcats.com/faqs.html</field><field name="title">www.swimmingcats.com/faqs.html&lt;!--INSERT TITLE--&gt;</field><field name="accessdate">2007-05-26</field></template></ref> <link label="Abyssinian (cat)">Abyssinians</link> are also reported to be more tolerant of water than most cats.</p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Impact of hunting</title>

<p>The domestic cat hunts and eats over a thousand <link label="Species">species</link>, many of them <link label="Invertebrate">invertebrate</link>s, especially insects — many <link label="Big cat">big cat</link>s will eat fewer than a hundred different species. Although theoretically big cats can kill most of these species as well, they often do not due to the relatively low nutritional content that smaller animals provide for the effort. An exception is the <link label="Leopard">leopard</link>, which commonly hunts rabbits and many other smaller animals. Even well-fed domestic cats may hunt and kill birds, mice, rats, scorpions, cockroaches, grasshoppers, and other small animals in their environment. </p>

<p>As a consequence of their exceptional hunting ability, cats can be quite destructive to <link label="Ecosystem">ecosystem</link>s in which they are not native, where local species have not had time to adapt to feline <link label="Introduced species">introduction</link>. In some cases, cats have contributed to or caused <link label="Extinction">extinction</link>s — for example, see the case of the <link label="Stephens Island Wren">Stephens Island Wren</link>. Due to their hunting behavior, in many countries feral cats are considered pests. Domestic cats are occasionally also required to have contained cat runs or to be kept inside entirely, as they can be hazardous to locally endangered bird species. For instance, various municipalities in <link label="Australia">Australia</link> have enacted such legislation. In some localities, owners fit their cat with a bell in order to warn prey of its approach (although some cats may figure out how and when the bell works, thereby learning more careful movements to avoid the ringing).</p>
</section></section><section depth="1"><title>House cats</title><section depth="2"><title>Domestication</title>

<p>In 2004, a grave was excavated in <link label="Cyprus">Cyprus</link> that contained the skeletons, laid close to one another, of both a human and a cat. The grave is estimated to be 9,500 years old, pushing back the earliest known feline-human association significantly.&lt;ref name=&quot;9500 years&quot;/&gt;<ref><template head="cite news"><field name="first">Hazel  </field><field name="last">Muir 
 </field><field name="authorlink"> </field><field name="coauthors"> </field><field name="title">Ancient remains could be oldest pet cat </field><field name="url">http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn4867.html </field><field name="work"> </field><field name="publisher"><link label="New Scientist">New Scientist</link> </field><field name="date">08 April 2004  </field><field name="accessdate">2007-11-23 </field></template></ref><ref><template head="cite news"><field name="first">Marsha</field><field name="last">Walton </field><field name="authorlink"> </field><field name="coauthors"> </field><field name="title">Ancient burial looks like human and pet cat </field><field name="url">http://edition.cnn.com/2004/TECH/science/04/08/cats.cyprus/index.html </field><field name="work"> </field><field name="publisher"><link label="CNN">CNN</link></field><field name="date">Friday, April 9, 2004</field><field name="accessdate">2007-11-23 </field></template> </ref></p>

<p>In captivity, indoor cats typically live 14 to 20 years, though the oldest-known cat lived to age 36.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title"> Feline Statistics </field><field name="url"> http://www.pawsonline.info/feline_statistics.htm </field><field name="accessdate"> 2005-08-15</field></template></ref> Domesticated cats tend to live longer if they are not permitted to go outdoors (reducing the risk of injury from fights or accidents and exposure to diseases) and if they are <link label="Neutering">neutered</link>. Some such benefits are: castrated male cats cannot develop <link label="Testicular cancer">testicular cancer</link>, spayed female cats cannot develop <link label="Ovarian cancer">ovarian cancer</link>, and both have a reduced risk of <link label="Mammary tumor">mammary cancer</link>.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title"> Spay and Neuter Your Pet Cats </field><field name="url">http://cats.about.com/od/reproduction/a/spay_neuter.htm</field></template></ref></p>

<p>Like some other domesticated animals, cats live in a <link label="Mutualism">mutualistic</link> arrangement with humans. It is believed that the benefit of removing rats and mice from humans' food stores outweighed the trouble of extending the protection of a human settlement to a formerly wild animal, almost certainly for humans who had adopted a farming economy. Unlike the dog, which also hunts and kills rodents, the cat does not eat grains, fruits, or vegetables. A cat that is good at hunting rodents is referred to as a mouser.<template head="Fact"><field name="date">December 2007</field></template></p>

<p>In modern rural areas, farms often have dozens of semi-feral cats. Hunting in the barns and the fields, they kill and eat rodents that would otherwise spoil large parts of the grain crop. Many pet cats successfully hunt and kill <link label="Rabbits">rabbits</link>, <link label="Rodents">rodents</link>, <link label="Bird">bird</link>s, <link label="Lizard">lizard</link>s, <link label="Frog">frog</link>s, <link label="Fish">fish</link>, and large <link label="Insect">insect</link>s by <link label="Instinct">instinct</link>, but might not eat their prey. They may even present their kills, dead or maimed, to their humans, perhaps expecting them to praise or reward them, or possibly even to complete the kill and eat the mouse.<template head="Fact"><field name="date">December 2007</field></template></p>

<p>In modern urban areas, some people find feral and free-roaming pet cats annoying and intrusive. Unaltered cats can engage in persistent nighttime calling (termed <link label="Caterwauling">caterwauling</link>) and defecation or &quot;marking&quot; of private property. Indoor confinement of pets and TNR (trap, neuter, return) programs for feral cats can help; some people also use <link label="Cat deterrent">cat deterrent</link>s to discourage cats from entering their property.</p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Interaction with humans</title>

<p>Human attitudes toward cats vary widely. Some people keep cats for casual companionship as <link label="Pet">pet</link>s. Others go to great lengths to pamper their cats, sometimes treating them as if they were children. Cats are also bred and shown as <link label="Cat registry">registered</link> pedigree pets, in a hobby known as the <link label="Animal fancy">cat fancy</link>.  </p>

<p>When a cat bonds with its human guardian, the cat may, at times, display behaviors similar to that of a human. Such behavior may include a trip to the litter box before bedtime or snuggling up close to its companion in bed or on the sofa. Other such behavior includes mimicking sounds of the owner or using certain sounds the cat picks up from the human; sounds representing specific needs of the cat, which the owner would recognize, such as a specific tone of <link label="Cat communication">meow</link> along with eye contact that may represent &quot;I'm hungry.&quot; The cat may also be capable of learning to communicate with the human using non-spoken language or <link label="Cat body language">body language</link> such as rubbing for affection (confirmation), facial expressions and making eye contact with the owner if something needs to be addressed (e.g., finding a bug crawling on the floor for the owner to get rid of). </p>

<p>Because of their small size, domesticated house cats pose almost no danger to adult humans — the main hazard is the possibility of infection (e.g., <link label="Cat scratch disease">cat scratch disease</link>, or, rarely, <link label="Rabies">rabies</link>) from a cat bite or scratch. Cats can also potentially inflict severe scratches or puncture an eye, though this is quite rare (although dogs have been known to be blinded by cats in fights, where the cat specifically and accurately targeted the eyes of the larger animal).</p>

<section depth="3"><title>Allergens</title>

<p><link label="Allergy">Allergic</link> reactions to cat <link label="Dander">dander</link> and/or cat saliva inspire one of the most common reasons people cite for disliking cats. Some humans who are <link label="Cat allergy">allergic to cats</link>—typically manifested by <link label="Hay fever">hay fever</link>, <link label="Asthma">asthma</link> or a skin <link label="Rash">rash</link>—quickly acclimate themselves to a particular animal and live comfortably in the same house with it, while retaining an allergy to cats in general.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url">http://www.animaltrustees.org/ATA_Web/pdfs/dealingwithcatallergies.pdf </field><field name="title">Dealing with cat allergies </field><field name="work">animaltrustees.org</field></template></ref>  Many humans find the rewards of cat companionship outweigh the discomfort and problems associated with these allergens. Some cope with the problem by taking prescription allergy medicine, along with bathing their cats frequently (weekly bathing will eliminate about 90% of the cat dander present in the environment).</p>
</section><section depth="3"><title>Trainability</title>

<p>Some owners seek to train their cat in performing tricks commonly exhibited by dogs, such as jumping, though this is rare. Individual cats have been known to learn to manipulate simple mechanisms, like sink faucets, by themselves or after prompting/encouraging. With effort and patience on the part of an owner, the average cat can usually be trained to at least obey simple commands such as &quot;get off the furniture&quot; or &quot;come to dinner&quot;. In general though, the seeming intractability of the ordinary house cat to training has long inspired the <link label="Simile">simile</link> &quot;like herding cats&quot;, as a general expression to describe any situation with a stubborn or uncooperative learner.</p>
</section></section><section depth="2"><title>Indoor scratching</title>

<p>As mentioned, cats are naturally driven to periodically hook their front claws into suitable surfaces and pull backwards, in order to clean the claws. Indoor cats benefit from being provided with a <link label="Scratching post">scratching post</link> so that they are less likely to use carpet or furniture which they can easily ruin.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title">Scratching or clawing in the house </field><field name="url">http://www.fabcats.org/scratching/index.php</field><field name="accessmonthday"><link label="August 14">August 14</link> </field><field name="accessyear"><link label="2005">2005</link> </field></template></ref> Commercial scratching posts typically are covered in carpeting or upholstery, but some authorities advise against this practice, as not making it clear to the cat which surfaces are permissible and which are not; they suggest using a plain wooden surface, or reversing the carpeting on the posts so that the rougher texture of the carpet backing is a more attractive alternative to the cat than the floor covering. Scratching posts made of <link label="Sisal">sisal</link> rope or <link label="Corrugated cardboard">corrugated cardboard</link> are also commonly found. Some indoor cats, however, especially those that were taken as kittens from feral colonies, may not understand the concept of a scratching post, and as a result will ignore it.</p>

<p><img src="Cat claw closeup.jpg">right|250px|thumb|Close-up of a cat's claw, with the quick clearly visible.</img>
Although scratching can serve cats to keep their claws from growing excessively long, their nails can be trimmed if necessary with a small nail trimmer designed for humans, or a small pair of electrician's <link label="Diagonal pliers">diagonal cutting pliers</link>, or a guillotine type cutter specifically designed for animal nail trimming. Care must always be taken to avoid cutting the <link label="Wiktionary:quick#Noun">quick</link> of the claw, analogous to cutting into the tip of a finger and equally painful and bloody. The position of the quick can be easily seen through the translucent nail of a cat with light colored claws but not in cats with dark colored nails, who therefore require carefully trimming of only small amounts from the nails. </p>
<section depth="3"><title>Declawing</title>

<template head="main"><link label="Onychectomy">Onychectomy</link></template>
<p>Declawing is a major surgery known as <i>onychectomy</i>, performed under <link label="Anesthesia">anesthesia</link>, which removes the tip of each digit (from the first knuckle out) of the cat's forepaws (and rarely the hind paws). The primary reason for declawing cats is to prevent them from damaging furniture; in the United States, some <link label="Landlord">landlord</link>s may require that tenants' cats be declawed. Rarely, vicious cats, cats that frequently fight with other pets, or cats that are too efficient at predation of songbirds etc. are declawed. This controversial procedure is uncommon outside of North America, and is prohibited by animal cruelty laws in <link label="Onychectomy#Legal status">many countries worldwide</link>.</p>

<p>An alternative to declawing is the application of blunt, vinyl nail caps that are affixed to the claws with nontoxic glue, requiring periodic replacement when the cat sheds its claw sheaths (about every four to six weeks). However, the cat will still experience difficulties because the capped nails are not as effective as claws.</p>
</section></section><section depth="2"><title>Waste</title>

<p>Indoor cats are usually provided with a <link label="Litter box">litter box</link> containing <link label="Cat litter">litter</link>, typically <link label="Bentonite">bentonite</link>, but sometimes other absorbent material such as shredded paper or wood chips, or sometimes <link label="Sand">sand</link> or similar material. This arrangement serves the same purpose as a toilet for humans. It should be cleaned daily and changed often, depending on the number of cats in a household and the type of litter; if it is not kept clean, a cat may be fastidious enough to find other locations in the house for urination or defecation. This may also happen for other reasons; for instance, if a cat becomes <link label="Constipation">constipated</link> and defecation is uncomfortable, it may associate the discomfort with the litter box and avoid it in favor of another location. A litterbox is recommended for indoor-outdoor cats as well. </p>

<p>Daily attention to the litter box also serves as a monitor of the cat's health. Numerous variations on litter and litter box design exist, including some which automatically sift the litter after each use. Bentonite or clumping litter is a variation which absorbs urine into clumps which can be sifted out along with feces, and thus stays cleaner longer with regular sifting, but has sometimes been reported to cause health problems in some cats.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title">Suspected bentonite toxicosis in a cat from ingestion of clay cat litter </field><field name="url">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=8888544&amp;dopt=Abstract</field><field name="accessmonthday"><link label="September 10">September 10</link> </field><field name="accessyear"><link label="2005">2005</link> </field></template></ref> </p>

<p><img src="Toilet Trained Cat 22 Aug 2005.jpg">thumb|250px|left|Toilet-trained house cat.</img>
Litterboxes may pose a risk of <link label="Toxoplasmosis">toxoplasmosis</link> transmission to susceptible pregnant women and immuno-compromised individuals. Most indoor-only cats would not normally be exposed to the disease and are not usually carriers. Transmission risk may be reduced by daily litterbox cleaning by someone other than the susceptible individual. </p>

<p>Some cats can be toilet trained, eliminating the litterbox and its attendant expense, unpleasant odor, and the need to use landfill space for disposal. Training may involve two or three weeks of incremental moves, such as moving and elevating the litterbox until it is near the toilet. For a short time, an adapter, such as a bowl or small box, may be used to suspend the litter above the toilet bowl but under the toilet seat. Several kits and other aids are marketed to help toilet-train cats. When training is complete, the cat uses the toilet by perching over the bowl.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title">Cat toilet-training </field><field name="url">http://www.karawynn.net/mishacat/toilet.html </field><field name="accessmonthday"><link label="August 8">August 8</link></field><field name="accessyear"><link label="2005">2005</link> </field></template></ref></p>

<p>However, as the <i><link label="Toxoplasma gondii">Toxoplasma gondii</link></i> parasite often found in cat droppings poses a threat to endangered <link label="Sea otter">sea otter</link>s&lt;ref name=mag72&gt;<template head="cite news"><field name="url">http://www.magazine.noaa.gov/stories/mag72.htm</field><field name="title">Parasite in cats killing sea otters</field><field name="publisher"><link label="National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration">National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration</link></field><field name="date">January 21, 2003</field><field name="work">NOAA magazine</field><field name="accessdate">2007-11-24</field></template>&lt;/ref&gt; cat owners in coastal areas are encouraged to dispose of droppings in the trash rather than flushing them.<ref>http://www.viamagazine.com/top_stories/articles/seaotter_savior07.asp</ref></p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Domesticated varieties</title>

<p>The <link label="List of cat breeds">list of cat breeds</link> is quite large: most cat registries actually recognize between 30 and 40 breeds of cats, and several more are in development, with one or more new breeds being recognized each year on average, having distinct features and heritage. The owners and breeders of show cats compete to see whose animal bears the closest resemblance to the &quot;ideal&quot; definition &amp; standard of the breed (see <link label="Selective breeding">selective breeding</link>). Because of common crossbreeding in populated areas, many cats are simply identified as belonging to the homogeneous breeds of <link label="Domestic longhair cat">domestic longhair</link> and <link label="Domestic shorthair cat">domestic shorthair</link>, depending on their type of fur. In the United Kingdom and Australia, non-purebred cats are referred in slang as <link label="Moggy">moggies</link> (derived from &quot;Maggie&quot;, short for Margaret, reputed to have been a common name for cows and calves in 18th century England and latter applied to housecats during the Victorian era).<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url">http://www.worldwidewords.org/qa/qa-mog1.htm
</field><field name="title">Moggie
</field><field name="publisher">Worldwidewords.org
</field><field name="accessdate">2007-05-15</field></template></ref> In the United States, a non-purebred cat is sometimes referred to in slang as a barn or alley cat, even if it is not a <link label="Feral cat">stray</link>.
Cats come in a variety of colors and patterns. These are physical properties and should not be confused with a breed of cat.
Some original cat breeds that have a distinct phenotype that is the main type occurring naturally as the dominant domesticated cat type in their region of origin are sometimes considered as subspecies and also have received names as such in nomenclature, although this is not supported by feline biologists.&lt;ref name=msw3/&gt; Some of these cat breeds are:
*<i>F. catus anura</i> - the Manx
*<i>F. catus siamensis</i> - the Siamese
*<i>F. catus cartusenensis</i> - the Chartreux
*<i>F. catus angorensis</i> - the Turkish Angora</p>
<section depth="3"><title>Coat patterns</title>

<p><img src="Greece-Cat.jpg">thumb|250px|Cat with a [[bicolor cat|van</img> pattern.]]<link label="Cat coat genetics">Cat coat genetics</link> can produce a variety of coat patterns. Some of the most common are:
; <link label="Bicolor cat">Bicolor, Tuxedo and Van</link> :This pattern varies between the <link label="Bicolor cat#Tuxedo cats">tuxedo cat</link> which is mostly black with a white chest, and possibly markings on the face and paws/legs, all the way to the <i>Van</i> pattern (so named after the <link label="Lake Van">Lake Van</link> area in Turkey, which gave rise to the <link label="Turkish Van">Turkish Van</link> breed), where the only colored parts of the cat are the tail (usually including the base of the tail proper), and the top of the head (often including the ears). There are several other terms for amounts of white between these two extremes, such as <i>Harlequin</i> or <i><link label="Jellicle">jellicle</link> cat</i>. Bicolor cats can have as their primary (non-white) color black, red, any dilution thereof and tortoiseshell (see below for definition).</p>

<p><img src="Felis silvestris - July 2007-1.jpg">thumb|250px|Mackerel tabby cat, showing the characteristic &quot;M&quot; on its forehead.</img>
; <link label="Tabby cat">Tabby cat</link> :Striped, with a variety of patterns. The classic &quot;blotched&quot; tabby (or &quot;marbled&quot;) pattern is the most common and consists of butterflies and bullseyes. The &quot;mackerel&quot; or &quot;striped&quot; tabby is a series of vertical stripes down the cat's side (resembling the fish). This pattern broken into spots is referred to as a &quot;spotted&quot; tabby. Finally, the tabby markings may look like a series of ticks on the fur, thus the &quot;ticked&quot; tabby, which is almost exclusively associated with the Abyssinian breed of cats. The worldwide evolution of the cat means that certain types of tabby are associated with certain countries; for instance, blotched tabbies are quite rare outside NW Europe, where they are the most common type.</p>

<p><img src="Curly calico2.gif">thumb|250px|Female tortoiseshell-and-white cat.</img>
; <link label="Tortoiseshell cat">Tortoiseshell and Calico</link>
: This cat is also known as a Calimanco cat or Clouded Tiger cat, and by the nickname &quot;tortie.&quot; In the cat fancy, a tortoiseshell cat is randomly patched over with red (or its dilute form, cream) and black (or its dilute blue) mottled throughout the coat. Additionally, the cat may have white spots in its fur, which make it a &quot;tortoiseshell and white&quot; cat or, if there is a significant amount of white in the fur and the red and black colors form a patchwork rather than a mottled aspect, the cat will be called a &quot;calico.&quot; All calicos are tortoiseshell (as they carry both black and red), but not all tortoiseshells are calicos (which requires a significant amount of white in the fur and patching rather than mottling of the colors). The calico is also sometimes called a &quot;tricolor cat.&quot; The Japanese refer to this pattern as <i>mi-ke</i> (meaning &quot;triple fur&quot;), while the Dutch call these cats <i>lapjeskat</i> (meaning &quot;patches cat&quot;). A true tricolor must consist of three colors: a reddish color, dark or light; white; and one other color, typically a brown, black or blue.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title">Torties, Calicos and Tricolor cats </field><field name="url">http://www.fanciers.com/cat-faqs/tricolors.shtml</field><field name="accessmonthday"><link label="October 24">October 24</link> </field><field name="accessyear"><link label="2005">2005</link> </field></template></ref> Both tortoiseshell and calico cats are typically female because the <link label="Coat (animal)">coat</link> pattern is the result of differential <link label="X chromosome">X chromosome</link> <link label="Lyonization">inactivation</link> in <link label="Female">female</link>s (which, as with all normal female <link label="Mammals">mammals</link>, have two X <link label="Chromosomes">chromosomes</link>). Conversely, cats where the overall color is ginger (orange) are commonly male (roughly in a 3:1 ratio). In a litter sired by a ginger tom, the females will be tortoiseshell or ginger. Male tortoiseshells can occur as a result of chromosomal abnormalities (often linked to sterility) or by a phenomenon known as chimericism, where two early stage embryos are merged into a single kitten. </p>

<p><img src="Niobe050905-Siamese Cat.jpeg">thumb|250px|Siamese cat, classical colorpoint pattern.</img>
;<link label="Point (coat color)">Colorpoint</link>
: The colorpoint pattern is most commonly associated with <link label="Siamese (cat)">Siamese</link> cats, but may also appear in any domesticated cat. A colorpointed cat has dark colors on the face, ears, feet, and tail, with a lighter version of the same color on the rest of the body, and possibly some white. The exact name of the colorpoint pattern depends on the actual color, so there are seal points (dark brown), chocolate points (warm lighter brown), blue points (dark gray), lilac or frost points (silvery gray-pink), red or flame points (orange), and tortie (tortoiseshell mottling) points, among others. This pattern is the result of a <link label="Mutation#Special classes">temperature sensitive mutation</link> in one of the <link label="Enzyme">enzyme</link>s in the <link label="Metabolic pathway">metabolic pathway</link> from <link label="Tyrosine">tyrosine</link> to pigment, such as <link label="Melanin">melanin</link>; thus, little or no pigment is produced except in the extremities or &quot;points,&quot; where the skin is slightly cooler. For this reason, colorpointed cats tend to darken with age as bodily temperature drops; also, the fur over a significant injury may sometimes darken or lighten as a result of temperature change. </p>

<p>:The tyrosine pathway also produces <link label="Neurotransmitter">neurotransmitter</link>s, thus mutations in the early parts of that pathway may affect not only pigment, but also neurological development. This results in a higher frequency of <link label="Strabismus">cross-eyes</link> among colorpointed cats, as well as the <link label="White tiger#Inbreeding depression">high frequency of cross-eyes in white tigers</link>. </p>

<p>White cats:
True albinism (a mutation of the tyrosinase gene) is quite rare in cats. Much more common is the appearance of white coat color due to a lack of <link label="Melanocytes">melanocytes</link> in the skin. A <link label="Melanin#Melanin deficiency in genetic disorders and disease states">higher frequency of deafness in white cats</link> is due to a reduction in the population and survival of melanoblast stem cells, which in addition to creating pigment producing cells, develop into a variety of neurological cell types. White cats with one or two blue eyes have a particularly high liklihood of being deaf.</p>
</section><section depth="3"><title>Body types</title>

<p>Cats can also come in several body types, ranging between two extremes:</p>

<p>; Oriental :Not a specific breed, but any cat with an elongated slender build, almond-shaped eyes, long nose, large ears (the <link label="Siamese (cat)">Siamese</link> and <link label="Oriental cat">Oriental Shorthair</link> breeds are examples of this).
; Cobby: Any cat with a short, muscular, compact build, roundish eyes, short nose, and small ears. <link label="Persian cat">Persian cat</link>s and <link label="Exotic cat">Exotic cat</link>s are two prime examples of such a body type.</p>
</section></section></section><section depth="1"><title>Feral cats</title>

<template head="Unreferencedsection"><field name="date">July 2007</field></template>
<template head="main"><link label="Feral cat">Feral cat</link></template>
<p><img src="Feral cat 4.jpg">Feral Cats at [[Kona</img>, <link label="Hawaii">Hawaii</link>.|left|thumb|270px]]
<link label="Feral cat">Feral cat</link>s may live alone, but most are found in large groups called <link label="Feral cat colony">feral colonies</link> with communal nurseries, depending on resource availability. Most abandoned cats probably have little alternative to joining a feral colony. Some feral cat colonies are found in large cities such as around the <link label="Colosseum">Colosseum</link> and <link label="Forum Romanum">Forum Romanum</link> in Rome. The Roman cats are not truly feral because they are partly fed and vetted by the local authority. Because cats are adaptable, those in residential areas know that if they are friendly to humans they need not worry about food or shelter. Some urban &quot;stray&quot; cats have many houses/humans to support them.</p>

<p>Although cats are adaptable, feral felines are unable to thrive in extreme cold and heat, and with a very high protein requirement, few find adequate nutrition on their own in cities. They are often killed by dogs, <link label="Coyote">coyote</link>s, and automobiles. However, there are thousands of volunteers and organizations that trap these unadoptable feral felines, <link label="Neutering">neutering</link> them, <link label="Immunization">immunize</link> the cats against rabies and <link label="Feline leukemia">feline leukemia</link>, and treat them with long-lasting <link label="Flea">flea</link> products. Before release back into their feral colonies, the attending veterinarian often nips the tip off one ear to mark the feral as neutered and inoculated, since these cats will more than likely find themselves trapped again. Volunteers continue to feed and give care to these cats throughout their lives, and not only is their lifespan greatly increased, but behavior and nuisance problems, due to competition for food, are also greatly reduced. In time, if an entire colony is successfully neutered, no additional kittens are born and the feral colony disappears.</p>
<section depth="2"><title>Environmental effects</title>

<p>&lt;!-- This section has been subject to extensive debate. Do not make changes to this section without first obtaining consensus on the Talk:Cat page. --&gt;
<img src="Feral cat gl3.gif">thumb|250px|Trapped Feral cat</img> </p>

<p>The environmental effects of feral cats vary greatly. In the <link label="Northern Hemisphere">Northern Hemisphere</link> most landmasses have fauna adapted to wildcat (<i>Felis sylvestris</i>) species and other placental mammal predators. The potential for environmental damage due to feral cats is arguably low, unless cat populations are very high, or the region supports unusually vulnerable native wildlife species. Feral cats are thought to be a major predator of <link label="Hawaii">Hawaii</link>an coastal and forest habitats, and are one species among many responsible for the decline of endemic forest bird species as well as seabirds like the <link label="Wedge-tailed Shearwater">Wedge-tailed Shearwater</link>.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url">http://www.birdinghawaii.co.uk/XShearwaterkills2.htm</field><field name="title">www.birdinghawaii.co.uk/XShearwaterkills2.htm&lt;!--INSERT TITLE--&gt;</field><field name="accessdate">2007-05-26</field></template></ref> In one study of 56 cats' <link label="Feces">feces</link>, the remains of 44 birds were found, 40 of which were <link label="Endemic birds of Hawaii">endemic species</link>.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url">http://www.earlham.edu/~biol/hawaii/mammals.htm
</field><field name="title">Introduced Species in Hawaii (Senior Seminar 2002)
</field><field name="year">2002
</field><field name="publisher">Earlham college, Department of Biology
</field><field name="accessdate">2007-05-15</field></template></ref> Fauna on islands of all sizes that are unfamiliar with felines as predators are particularly vulnerable to feral cats.<template head="Fact"><field name="date">November 2007</field></template></p>


<p>In the <link label="Southern Hemisphere">Southern Hemisphere</link> there are many landmasses including <link label="Australia">Australia</link> where cat species have never been native, and other placental mammalian predators were rare or absent. Native species there tend to be more ecologically vulnerable and behaviorally &quot;naive&quot; to predation by feral cats. Feral cats have had serious affects on these wildlife species and have played a leading role in the endangerment and extinction of many of them.<template head="Fact"><field name="date">November 2007</field></template> In Australia a large quantity of native birds, lizards and small marsupials are taken every year by feral cats, and feral cats have played a role in driving some small marsupial species to extinction.<template head="Fact"><field name="date">November 2007</field></template> Some organizations in Australia are now going to effort of creating fenced islands of habitat for endangered species that are free of feral cats and foxes.<template head="Fact"><field name="date">November 2007</field></template></p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Ethical and humane concerns over feral cats</title>

<p>There are two divergent views about the relationship of cats with the <link label="Natural environment">natural environment</link>. The first argues that the environmental impact of feral cat programs and of indoor/outdoor cats is a subject of debate. Part of this stems from humane concern for the cats, and part stems from concerns about cat predation on endangered species. Nearly all studies agree that abandoned animals lead hard lives.<template head="Fact"><field name="date">September 2007</field></template> The amount of ecological damage done by indoor/outdoor cats depends on local conditions. As suggested above, the most severe effect occurs to island ecologies.<template head="Fact"><field name="date">September 2007</field></template> Environmental concerns may be minimal in most of the UK where cats are an established species and few to none of the local prey species are endangered. Pet owners can contact veterinarians, ecological organizations, and universities for opinions about whether local conditions are suitable for outdoor cats. Additional concerns include potential dangers from larger predators and infectious diseases. <link label="Coyotes">Coyotes</link> kill large numbers of housecats in the Southwestern <link label="United States">United States</link>, even in urban zones. FELV (feline leukemia), FIV (feline immunodeficiency virus), or <link label="Rabies">rabies</link> may be present in the area. If faced with conflicting evidence, the safe choice is to keep a cat indoors. Experts recommend a gradual transition to indoor life for cats who are accustomed to going outside.<template head="Fact"><field name="date">September 2007</field></template> </p>

<p>&lt;!-- This section has been subject to extensive debate. Do not make changes to this section without first obtaining consensus on the Talk:Cat page. --&gt;
Cats present a risk of overpopulation, as well. According to the Humane Society of the United States, 3–4 million cats and dogs are <link label="Animal euthanasia">euthanized</link> each year in the United States and many more are confined to cages in shelters because there are significantly more animals being born than there are homes. 
Neutering pets helps keep the overpopulation down. A study in <link label="1992">1992</link> found that in the USA, 12,893 (29.4%) of pets, 26.9% of dogs and 32.6% of cats were sterilized.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="url">http://www.spayusa.org/main_directory/02-facts_and_education/stats_surveys/javma_articles/02dogs-cats-sterilized.asp
</field><field name="title">Estimation of the proportions of dogs and cats that are surgically sterilized
</field><field name="author">Jane C. Mahlow, DVM, MS
</field><field name="publisher">www.spayusa.org, summarizing J Am Vet Med Assoc 1992;215;640–643
</field><field name="accessdate">2007-05-15</field></template></ref>
Local humane societies, <link label="SPCA">SPCA</link>s, and other animal protection organizations urge people to neuter their pets and to adopt from shelters instead of purchasing elsewhere.</p>
</section></section><section depth="1"><title>Etymology and taxonomic history</title><section depth="2"><title>Scientific classification</title>

<p>The domesticated cat was previously classified as <i>Felis catus</i> by <link label="Carolus Linnaeus">Carolus Linnaeus</link> in his <i><link label="Systema Naturae">Systema Naturae</link></i> of 1758.<ref><template head="la icon"></template><template head="cite book"><field name="last"> Linnaeus </field><field name="first"> C </field><field name="authorlink"> Carolus Linnaeus </field><field name="title"> Systema naturae per regna tria naturae, secundum classes, ordines, genera, species, cum characteribus, differentiis, synonymis, locis. Tomus I. Editio decima, reformata. </field><field name="publisher"> Holmiae. (Laurentii Salvii). </field><field name="date"> 1758 </field><field name="pages"> 824 </field><field name="url"> http://books.google.com/books?id=Ix0AAAAAQAAJ</field></template></ref> <link label="Johann Christian Daniel von Schreber">Johann Christian Daniel von Schreber</link> named the Wildcat <i>Felis silvestris</i> in 1775. However, in opinion 2027 (published in Volume 60, Part 1 of the <i>Bulletin of Zoological Nomenclature</i>, <link label="March 31">March 31</link>, <link label="2003">2003</link><ref><template head="cite journal"><field name="last"> ICZN </field><field name="title"> OPINION 2027: Usage of 17 specific names based on wild species which are pre-dated by or contemporary with those based on domestic Animals (Lepidoptera, Osteichthyes, Mammalia): conserved </field><field name="journal"> Bulletin of Zoological Nomenclature </field><field name="volume"> 60 </field><field name="issue"> 1 </field><field name="publisher"> <link label="International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature">International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature</link> </field><field name="date"> <link label="2003-03-31">2003-03-31</link> </field><field name="accessdate"> 2006-07-13 </field><field name="url"> http://www.iczn.org/BZNMar2003opinions.htm#opinion2027</field></template></ref>) the International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature &quot;conserved the usage of 17 specific names based on wild species, which are predated by or contemporary with those based on domestic forms&quot;, thus confirming <i>F. silvestris</i> for the Wildcat and <i>F. silvestris catus</i> for its domesticated cousin. </p>

<p><link label="Johann Christian Polycarp Erxleben">Johann Christian Polycarp Erxleben</link> classified the domesticated cat as <i>Felis domesticus</i> in his <i>Anfangsgründe der Naturlehre and Systema regni animalis</i> of 1777. This name, and its variants <i>Felis catus domesticus</i> and <i>Felis silvestris domesticus</i>, are often seen, but they are not valid scientific names under the rules of the <link label="International Code of Zoological Nomenclature">International Code of Zoological Nomenclature</link>.</p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Nomenclature</title>

<p>A group of cats is referred to as a <b>clowder</b>, a male cat is called a <b>tom</b> (or a <b>gib</b>, if neutered), and a female is called a <b>queen</b>. The male progenitor of a cat, especially a pedigreed cat, is its <b>sire</b>, and its female progenitor is its <b>dam</b>. An immature cat is called a <b><link label="Kitten">kitten</link></b> (which is also an alternative name for young <link label="Rat">rat</link>s, <link label="Rabbit">rabbit</link>s, <link label="Hedgehog">hedgehog</link>s, <link label="Beaver">beaver</link>s, <link label="Squirrel">squirrel</link>s and <link label="Skunk">skunk</link>s). In <link label="Britain in the Middle Ages">medieval Britain</link>, the word <i>kitten</i> was interchangeable with the word <i>catling</i>. A cat whose <link label="Genealogy">ancestry</link> is formally registered is called a <link label="Pedigree (cat)">pedigreed cat</link>, <link label="Purebred cat">purebred cat</link>, or a <link label="Show cat">show cat</link> (although not all show cats are pedigreed or purebred). In strict terms, a purebred cat is one whose ancestry contains only individuals of the same breed. A pedigreed cat is one whose ancestry is recorded, but may have ancestors of different breeds (almost exclusively new breeds; cat registries are very strict about which breeds can be mated together). Cats of unrecorded mixed ancestry are referred to as <link label="Domestic longhair cat">domestic longhairs</link> and <link label="Domestic shorthair cat">domestic shorthairs</link> or commonly as random-bred, moggies, <link label="Mongrel">mongrel</link>s, mutt-cats or alley cats. The ratio of pedigree/purebred cats to random-bred cats varies from country to country. However, generally speaking, purebreds are less than ten percent of the total Feline population.<ref><i>ASPCA Complete Guide to Cats</i> by James R. Richards,, DVM</ref></p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Etymology</title>

<p>The word <i>cat</i> derives from <link label="Old English">Old English</link> <i>catt</i>, which belongs to a group of related words in European languages, including Welsh <i>cath</i>, Spanish <i>gato</i>, Basque <i>katu</i>, <link label="Byzantine Greek">Byzantine Greek</link> <i>kátia</i>, <link label="Old Irish">Old Irish</link> <i>cat</i>, <link label="German language">German</link> <i>Katze</i>, and <link label="Old Church Slavonic">Old Church Slavonic</link> <i>kotka</i>. The ultimate source of all these terms is <link label="Vulgar Latin">Late Latin</link> <i>catus, cattus, catta</i> &quot;domestic cat&quot;, as opposed to <i>feles</i> &quot;European wildcat&quot;. It is unclear whether the Greek or the Latin came first, but they were undoubtedly borrowed from an <link label="Afro-Asiatic languages">Afro-Asiatic</link> language akin to <link label="Old Nubian language">Nubian</link> <i>kadís</i> and <link label="Berber languages">Berber</link> <i>kaddîska</i>, both meaning &quot;wildcat&quot;.<ref><template head="cite web"><field name="title"> Cat </field><field name="url"> http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=cat </field><field name="work"> <external href="http://www.etymonline.com/index.php">The Online etymology dictionary</external> </field><field name="accessdate"> 2007-05-15</field></template></ref>  This term was either cognate with or borrowed from <link label="Late Egyptian">Late Egyptian</link> <i>čaus</i> &quot;jungle cat, African wildcat&quot; (later giving <link label="Coptic language">Coptic</link> <i>šau</i> &quot;tomcat&quot;<ref>Crum, Walter Ewing. <i>A Coptic Dictionary</i>. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1939: 601 &lt;http://www.metalog.org/files/crum/601.gif&gt;</ref>), itself from earlier <link label="Ancient Egyptian language">Egyptian</link> <i>tešau</i> &quot;female cat&quot;<ref>&quot;Le chat: origines et étymologie.&quot; <i>Chat et compagnie</i>. 2006. &lt;http://www.chat-et-cie.fr/chat.htm&gt;</ref> (vs. <i>miew</i> &quot;tomcat&quot;<ref>SenenAnep Meritamen. &quot;English to Egyptian Dictionary.&quot; posted 29 August 2004. <i>Ancient Worlds</i>. AncientWorlds LLC, 2002 &lt;http://www.ancientworlds.net/399761&gt;.</ref>).</p>

<p>The term <i>puss</i> (as in pussycat) may come from <link label="Dutch language">Dutch</link> <i>poes</i> or from <link label="Low German">Low German</link> <i>Puuskatte</i>, dialectal <link label="Swedish language">Swedish</link> <i>kattepus</i>, or <link label="Norwegian language">Norwegian</link> <i>puse</i>, <i>pusekat</i>, all of which primarily denote a woman and, by extension, a female cat.<ref><i>Webster's Encyclopedic Unabridged Dictionary of the English Language</i>. New York: Gramercy Books, 1996: 1571.</ref></p>
</section></section><section depth="1"><title>History and mythology</title>

<p><img src="Egypte louvre 058.jpg">thumb|250px|Egyptian sculpture at the [[Louvre</img>.]]
<template head="main"><link label="History of cats">Cats in ancient Egypt</link></template>
Cats have been kept by humans since at least <link label="Ancient Egypt">ancient Egypt</link>, where the mythical cat <link label="Bast (goddess)">Bast</link> was goddess of the home, the domesticated cat, protector of the fields and home from vermin infestations, and sometimes took on the warlike aspect of a lioness. The first domesticated cats may have saved early Egyptians from many rodent infestations and likewise, Bast developed from the adoration for her feline companions. She was the daughter of the sun god <link label="Ra">Ra</link> and played significant role in <link label="Ancient Egyptian religion">Ancient Egyptian religion</link>. It has been speculated that cats resident in Kenya's Islands in the <link label="Lamu Archipelago">Lamu Archipelago</link> may be the last living direct descendants of the cats of ancient Egypt.&lt;ref name = lamu&gt;<template head="cite book"><field name="last"> Couffer </field><field name="first"> Jack</field><field name="title"> The Cats of Lamu</field><field name="publisher"> The Lyons Press </field><field name="date"> 1998 </field><field name="location"> New York</field><field name="id"> ISBN 1558216626 </field></template>&lt;/ref&gt;</p>

<p>Several ancient religions believed that cats are exalted souls, companions or guides for humans, that they are all-knowing but are mute so they cannot influence decisions made by humans. In <link label="Japan">Japan</link>, the <link label="Maneki Neko">Maneki Neko</link> is a cat that is a symbol of &quot;good fortune&quot;. While in Islam there is not a sacred species, it is said by some writers that <link label="Muhammad">Muhammad</link> had a favorite cat, <link label="Muezza">Muezza</link>.<ref><template head="cite book"><field name="author"> Geyer, Georgie Anne </field><field name="year"> 2004 </field><field name="title"> When Cats Reigned Like Kings: On the Trail of the Sacred Cats</field></template></ref> It is said he loved cats so much that &quot;he would do without his cloak rather than disturb one that was sleeping on it&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reeves&quot;&gt;<template head="cite book"><field name="author"> Minou Reeves </field><field name="title"> Muhammad in Europe </field><field name="publisher"> New York University (NYU) Press </field><field name="pages"> p.52</field></template>&lt;/ref&gt;</p>
<section depth="2"><title>Nine Lives</title>
<p>It is common lore that cats have nine lives. This is a tribute to their perceived durability, their occasional apparent lack of the instinct for self-preservation, and their seeming ability to survive falls that would be fatal to other animals.</p>

<p>This disregard for safety is common in animals of cats' size and smaller. A cat is about the largest animal that can fall from any height with a significant chance of survival. Their surface area to volume ratio is generally large, and consequently their terminal velocity when falling is fairly small. Their bones are less calcified than in larger animals, so they can elastically absorb more energy.</p>
</section></section><section depth="1"><title>See also</title>
<p>* <link label="Cat genetics">Cat genetics</link>
* <link label="Cat breed">Cat breed</link>
* <link label="Cat Fanciers' Association">Cat Fanciers' Association</link>
* <link label="Cat meat">Cat meat</link>
* <link label=":Category:Cat types">Cat types</link>
* <link label="Feline ethology">Feline ethology</link>
* <link label="List of cat breeds">List of cat breeds</link>
* <link label="List of historical cats">List of historical cats</link>
* <link label="List of fictional cats">List of fictional cats</link>
* <link label="Sex organ of cat">Sex organ of cat</link>
* <link label="Cat pheromone">Cat pheromone</link>
* <link label="Cat intelligence">Cat intelligence</link>
* <link label="Cat play and toys">Cat play and toys</link></p>
</section><section depth="1"><title>References</title>
<template head="reflist"><field>2</field></template>
</section><section depth="1"><title>External links</title>
<template head="wiktionarypar"><field>cat</field><field>kitty</field><field>meow</field></template> 
<template head="Wikibooks"><field>Animal Care</field></template>
<template head="wikiquote"></template>
<template head="commonscat"><field>Felis silvestris catus</field></template>
<template head="wikispecies"><field>Felis sylvestris catus</field><field>Cat</field></template>
<section depth="2"><title>Anatomy</title>
<p>*<external href="http://brainmaps.org/index.php?p=speciesdata&amp;species=felis-catus">High-Resolution Images of the Cat Brain</external></p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Articles</title>
<p>*<external href="http://www.albertastars.com/galleries/cats-predatory-behavior/">Predatory Behavior of Cats Explained (with pictures)</external> on <external href="http://www.albertastars.com/">Alberta Stars</external>
*<external href="http://en.citizendium.org/wiki/Choosing_a_cat">Choosing a cat</external> - article at <i><link label="Citizendium">Citizendium</link></i>
*<external href="http://www.catpert.com">Catpert. The Cat Expert</external> - Cat articles
*<external href="http://www.xmission.com/~emailbox/whycat.htm">Cat behavior explained</external></p>
</section><section depth="2"><title>Veterinary related</title>
<p>*<external href="http://www.aafponline.org/">American Association of Feline Practitioners</external>
*<external href="http://home.ncifcrf.gov/ccr/lgd/comparative_genome/catgenome/index_n.asp">Cat Genome Project</external> at the US <external href="http://www.cancer.gov/">The National Cancer Institute</external>
*<external href="http://www.vet.cornell.edu/fhc/">Cornell Feline Health Center</external>
*<external href="http://maxshouse.com/Database_toc.htm">Feline Medical &amp; Behaviour Database</external> (large number of short articles)
*<external href="http://www.petcat.us/questions.shtml">Information about the third eyelid of cats, and the problem of Kertao, or &quot;dry eye&quot;.</external>
*<external href="http://www.peteducation.com/article.cfm?cls=0&amp;cat=1763&amp;articleid=1108">Onions are Toxic to Cats</external>
*<external href="http://www.aafponline.org/resources/guidelines/Feline_Behavior_Guidelines.pdf">Feline Behavior Guidelines</external> An <link label="AAFP">AAFP</link> publication
*<external href="http://www.animalhospitals-usa.com/cats/cat_vaccination.html">Cat Vaccination and Health Care Schedule</external></p>


<template head="Cat nav"></template>

<p>

</p>

<template head="Link FA"><field>es</field></template>
<template head="Link FA"><field>ru</field></template>
<template head="Link FA"><field>sk</field></template>
<template head="Link FA"><field>sr</field></template>
<template head="Link FA"><field>hu</field></template>
<p><link label="Als:Hauskatze">als:Hauskatze</link>
<link label="Ang:Catte">ang:Catte</link>
<link label="Ar:قطة">ar:قطة</link>
<link label="An:Gato">an:Gato</link>
<link label="Frp:Chat">frp:Chat</link>
<link label="Ast:Gatu">ast:Gatu</link>
<link label="Az:Pişik">az:Pişik</link>
<link label="Bm:Jakuma">bm:Jakuma</link>
<link label="Zh-min-nan:Niau">zh-min-nan:Niau</link>
<link label="Bar:Katz">bar:Katz</link>
<link label="Bo:ཞི་མི་">bo:ཞི་མི་</link>
<link label="Br:Kazh">br:Kazh</link>
<link label="Bg:Котка">bg:Котка</link>
<link label="Ca:Gat">ca:Gat</link>
<link label="Cs:Kočka domácí">cs:Kočka domácí</link>
<link label="Co:Ghjattu">co:Ghjattu</link>
<link label="Cy:Cath">cy:Cath</link>
<link label="Da:Kat">da:Kat</link>
<link label="De:Hauskatze">de:Hauskatze</link>
<link label="Et:Kass">et:Kass</link>
<link label="El:Γάτα">el:Γάτα</link>
<link label="Eml:Gàt">eml:Gàt</link>
<link label="Es:Felis silvestris catus">es:Felis silvestris catus</link>
<link label="Eo:Hejma kato">eo:Hejma kato</link>
<link label="Eu:Katu">eu:Katu</link>
<link label="Fa:گربه">fa:گربه</link>
<link label="Fr:Chat">fr:Chat</link>
<link label="Fur:Gjat">fur:Gjat</link>
<link label="Gl:Gato">gl:Gato</link>
<link label="Zh-classical:貓">zh-classical:貓</link>
<link label="Hak:Meu-é">hak:Meu-é</link>
<link label="Ko:고양이">ko:고양이</link>
<link label="Hr:Domaća mačka">hr:Domaća mačka</link>
<link label="Io:Kato">io:Kato</link>
<link label="Id:Kucing">id:Kucing</link>
<link label="Ia:Catto">ia:Catto</link>
<link label="Os:Гæды">os:Гæды</link>
<link label="Is:Köttur">is:Köttur</link>
<link label="It:Felis sylvestris catus">it:Felis sylvestris catus</link>
<link label="He:חתול">he:חתול</link>
<link label="Jv:Kucing">jv:Kucing</link>
<link label="Ka:კატა">ka:კატა</link>
<link label="Ht:Chat">ht:Chat</link>
<link label="La:Feles">la:Feles</link>
<link label="Lv:Kaķis">lv:Kaķis</link>
<link label="Lb:Hauskaz">lb:Hauskaz</link>
<link label="Lt:Katė">lt:Katė</link>
<link label="Ln:Nkɔ́ndɔkɔ́">ln:Nkɔ́ndɔkɔ́</link>
<link label="Hu:Macska">hu:Macska</link>
<link label="Mg:Saka">mg:Saka</link>
<link label="Ml:പൂച്ച">ml:പൂച്ച</link>
<link label="Mt:Qattus">mt:Qattus</link>
<link label="Mr:मांजर">mr:मांजर</link>
<link label="Mzn:بامشی">mzn:بامشی</link>
<link label="Ms:Kucing">ms:Kucing</link>
<link label="Cdo:Mà">cdo:Mà</link>
<link label="Nl:Kat">nl:Kat</link>
<link label="Nds-nl:Kat">nds-nl:Kat</link>
<link label="Ja:ネコ">ja:ネコ</link>
<link label="No:Tamkatt">no:Tamkatt</link>
<link label="Nn:Katt">nn:Katt</link>
<link label="Nrm:Cat">nrm:Cat</link>
<link label="Uz:Mushuk">uz:Mushuk</link>
<link label="Km:ឆ្មា">km:ឆ្មា</link>
<link label="Nds:Katt">nds:Katt</link>
<link label="Pl:Kot">pl:Kot</link>
<link label="Pt:Gato doméstico">pt:Gato doméstico</link>
<link label="Ro:Pisică de casă">ro:Pisică de casă</link>
<link label="Qu:Michi">qu:Michi</link>
<link label="Ru:Кошка">ru:Кошка</link>
<link label="Se:Bussá">se:Bussá</link>
<link label="Sco:Cat">sco:Cat</link>
<link label="St:Katse">st:Katse</link>
<link label="Sq:Macja">sq:Macja</link>
<link label="Scn:Jattu">scn:Jattu</link>
<link label="Simple:Cat">simple:Cat</link>
<link label="Sd:ٻلي">sd:ٻلي</link>
<link label="Sk:Mačka domáca">sk:Mačka domáca</link>
<link label="Sl:Domača mačka">sl:Domača mačka</link>
<link label="Sr:Мачка">sr:Мачка</link>
<link label="Fi:Kissa">fi:Kissa</link>
<link label="Sv:Katt">sv:Katt</link>
<link label="Ta:பூனை">ta:பூனை</link>
<link label="Th:แมว">th:แมว</link>
<link label="Vi:Mèo">vi:Mèo</link>
<link label="Chr:ᏪᏌ">chr:ᏪᏌ</link>
<link label="Tl:Pusa">tl:Pusa</link>
<link label="Tr:Kedi">tr:Kedi</link>
<link label="Uk:Домашня кішка">uk:Домашня кішка</link>
<link label="Wa:Tchet">wa:Tchet</link>
<link label="Bat-smg:Katie">bat-smg:Katie</link>
<link label="Zh:猫">zh:猫</link></p></section></section></text><catlinks><catlink href="Category:Cats"/><catlink href="Category:Invasive animal species"/><catlink href="Category:Cosmopolitan species"/></catlinks>
    </revision>
  </page>
